Guide to the Juana de Ibarbourou Papers, 1915-1960 M0642
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Juana de Ibarbourou papers
1915-1960
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
M0642
4.5 Linear Feet
Prominent Correspondents
No Subnote Content
General note
Correspondents are listed alphabetically by country and thereunder by author's surname
Argentina
Berdiales, German
Gonzales Carbalho, José
Paz, Carlos Rojas
Prilutzky, Julia
Tiempo, Cesar
Walsh, Maria Elena
Bolivia
Roberto Hinojosa
Santa Cruz, Luis Mendizabal
Brazil
de Carvalho, Alberto
de Castro, Aloysio
Julio, Silvio
Lima, Jorge de
Ornellas, Manoelito de
Soares, Jose Roberto de Macedo
Chile
Casanueva, Humberto Diaz
Corvalan, Stella
Espejo, Washington
Flores, Alberto Baeza
Ladron de Guevara, Matilde
Letelier, Ligia
Mistral, Gabriela
Morgan, Patricia
Undurraga, Antonio de
Columbia
Arcinegas, Ismael Enrique
Cabellero, Agustin Nieto
Carvajal, Mario
Delmar, Meira
Hispano, Cornelio (Ismael Lopez)
Llanos, Antonio
Meza, Juan Bautista Jaramillo
Costa Rica
Urgalde G., Raul
Vincenzi, Moises
Cuba
Acosta, Ofelia Rodriguez
Aloma, Mariblanca Sabas
de Bustamante, Antonio S.
Estenger, Rafael
Fontanilles, Jose Conanglia
Godoy, Armand
Hernandez-Cata, Alfonso
Jauma, Ricardo Riano
Mora, Jesus Saiz de la
Morandeyra, Mary
Perez, Jose Cid
Rio, Pastor del
Rios, Maria Alvarez
Santovenia, Emeterio S.
Vidaurreta, Juan Marinello
Dominican Republic
Cabral, Manuel del
Echavarria, Miguel R. Perez
Fiallo, Fabio
Gimenez, R. Emilio
Lopez-Penha, Haim
Urena, Pedro Henriquez
Ecuador
Andrada, Jorge Carrerra
Arias, Augusto
Gallegos, Gerardo
Icaza, Rosa Borja de
Frances
Gilles, Albert
Lasserre, Jean Bernard
Miomandre, Francis de
Honduras
Barrerra, Claudio
de Miralda, Paca (Navas)
Mexico
Dromundo, Baltasar
Garibay, Cesar
Hernandez, Adolfo Ornelas
Junco, Alfonso
Plancarte, Gabriel Mendez
Pren, Jose Esquivel
Reyes, Alfonso
Reyes, Bernardo
Valle, Rafael Heliodoro
Panama
Geenzier, Enrique
Obaldia, Maria Olympia de
Paraguay
Cabeda, Adalita Ayala
de Fracchia, Ida Talavera
Gonzalez, Natalicio
O'Leary, Juan E.
Pla, Josefina
Recalde, Fecundo
Peru
Bustamante y Ballivian, Enrique
Bustamante y Rivero, J.L.
Calderon, Ventura Garcia
Champion, Emilio
Colmenares, Delia
Doreste, Julia
Eguren, Jose Maria
Guillen, Alberto
Hernandez, Jose A.
Marmol, Matilde
Palma, Angelica
Portal, Magda
Rojas, Rosa Maria
Sanchez, Luis Alberto
Valle, Arnaldo del
Vargas, Augusto Tamayo
Xammar, Luis F.
Poland
Pazurkiewicz, Stanislaus
Puerto Rico
Ceide, Amelia
Cuesta, J. Enamorado
Labarthe, Pedro Juan
Ramos, Ramon Delgado
Villaronga, Luis
Spain
Aller, Angel
Azua, Luis Jimenez de
Diez-Canedo, Enrique
Fraga, German Fernandez
Guillen, Jorge
Torre, Guillermo de
Uruguay
Acosta (Lauxar), Osvaldo Crispo
Ballesteros, Adolfo Montiel
Bardesio, Orfilia
Belinzon, Concepcion Silva
Bustamante, Raul Montero
Caceres, Esther de
Casal, Julio J.
Cione, Otto Miguel
Felde, Alberto Zum
Lasplaces, Alberto
Monegal, Jose
Oribe, Emilio
Quijano, Carlos
Rodriguez, Jose Pereira
Valdes, Fernan Silva
Uruguayan Residents in Paris
Barbagelata, Hugo D.
Deambrosis-Martins, Carlos
Supervielle, Jules
U.S.S.R.
Ignatof, Sergio S.
Venezuela
Aristeguieta, Jean
Arraiz, Antonio
Blanco, Andres Eloy
Blanco-Fombona, Rufino
Cordoba, Diego
Cova, J.A.
Davila, Vicente
Larriva, Enriqueta Arvelo
Picon-Salas, Mariano
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The collection includes correspondence, which mention her works, her name change to Juana de America, her candidacy for the Nobel Prize, invites asking for her collaboration on works, and poems which mention her; documents and correspondence regarding her works; awards and honors; music; newsclippings; telegrams; and book dedications from other authors.
BIOGRAPHY
Juana de Ibarbourou was born in Uruguay in 1895. She grew up in the country-side and began to feel an affinity with nature at an early age. She wrote lyrics celebrating life, love, and nature. Her early works, including "Las lenguas de diamante" (1919) and "Raiz salvaje" (1922), give a sense of joyousness about human existence and, in 1923, earned her the name of Juana de America. She wrote for magazines, newspapers, and also wrote children's tales and textbooks.
Her poetry is based on what she has seen or experienced, and she uses nature to reflect her thoughts, emotions, and moods. Her later works were influenced by religion as well as a growing preoccupation with old age, pain, death, bitterness and sorrow. She died in 1979.
ABSTRACT
Uruguyan poet, born in de Melo (Departamento de Cerro Largo). Her first book, Las Lenguas de Diamante, was published in Bueons Aires in 1919. Highly regarded by both Latin American and European critics, she became one of the most prestigious figures of Uruguayan literature.
Includes incoming correspondence (ca. 2100 letters), manuscripts, corrected galleys, reviews, awards, musical compositions, newsclippings, cards, and photographs.
Provenance:
Purchased, 1992.
Access Restrictions:
None.
Poets, Uruguayan; Uruguayan poetry -20th century; Uruguayan literature -20th century; Plá, Alfonso; Portal, Magda; Mistral, Gabriela; Andrada, Jorge Carrera; Pic on-Salas, Mariano; Díaz Casanueva, Humberto; Eguren, José Marí; Arraiz, Antonio; Reyes, Alfonso; Cabral, Manuel del
- Correspondence, 1910, 1911, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1910, 1911, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1951-1953 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Newspaper articles (Box 5, Folder 1-7)
- Newspaper articles (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
- Programs and announcements (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
- Invitations (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Poems (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Magazine articles (Box 7, Folder 1-7)
- Book of accounts (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Telegrams (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Book dedications from other authors (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
- Texts written and edited by Juana de Ibarbourou (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Awards and honors (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Correspondence regarding her works (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Musical works (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Visiting cards (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Holiday cards and postcards (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Official bank cards and passports (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Napkins and souvenirs (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Photographs and some artwork (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Various receipts (Box 9, Folder 6-7)
- 5 books by Ibarbourou (Box 10)